Guide to the Edward F. Dobihal, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward F. Dobihal, Jr. papers
1964-2005
1971-1973
MS 1683
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.06
(13 boxes)
The papers consist of scattered correspondence, minutes, reports, writings and audiocassettes primarily documenting Edward Dobihal's involvement with, and the early administrative history of, Connecticut Hospice, Inc. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Dobihal, Edward F., 1927-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward F. Dobihal, Jr., 1995, 1996, 1999, 2001, 2002, and 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection is mainly open, material in box 2 of Accession 1996-M-128 is closed until January 1, 2057.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in by accession, alphabetically thereunder.
Biographical / Historical
Reverend Edward F. Dobihal, Jr., received his B.A. from American University in 1949, his B.D. from Drew Theological Seminary in 1952, and his Ph.D. from Drew University in 1965. Prior to his arrival at Yale, he served as pastor of the Lafayette Methodist Church in Jersey City, New Jersey, and as chaplain at St. Elizabeth's Hospital in Washington, D.C. He was chaplain at Yale-New Haven Hospital from 1964 to 1967, and from 1967 to 1990, was director of the department of religious ministries in the hospital, and associate clinical professor and clinical professor of pastoral care at Yale Divinity School. Thereafter he served as pastoral consultant to the Yale School of Nursing and to the department of religious ministries in Yale-New Haven Hospital. For many years he specialized in care for the dying and, in 1971, was instrumental in the founding of Connecticut Hospice, Inc., the first hospice established in the United States. He was the first chairman of the board of directors of the hospice and later was made an honorary lifetime member of the board
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of scattered correspondence, minutes, reports, and writings primarily documenting Edward Dobihal's involvement with, and the early administrative history of, Connecticut Hospice, Inc. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection
Hospice care; Hospices (Terminal care); Terminal care; Dobihal, Edward F., 1927-; Connecticut Hospice
- Original Accession, 1970-1982; Accession 1995-M-111
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    - General, 1971-1972, 1978-1979, 1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Budget/Funding, 1971, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Committee A - Hospice Planners, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Newsletters, 1973-1975, 1977-1978, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Philosophy statement, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Regional Hospice Development Program - progress report and program plan, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Staff, 1971, 1973, 1975, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Steering committee, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Structure committee, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Task forces
      - Patient Care, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Professional Relations, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Research, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Patient care, 1972, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - St. Christopher's Hospice, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - United States Senate - Committee on Aging [includes Dobihal's testimony], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Additional material, Accession 1996-M-128
  - Articles about Dobihal, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    - General, Circa 1971-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Employee grievance, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Material is restricted until January 1, 2057.
    - Site plans, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - St. Christopher's Hospice [interviews with staff], undated (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Writings on hospice care
    - General, Circa 1972-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Children, 1966-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dobihal, Edward, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Saunders, Cecily, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Slides, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional material, Accession 2000-M-082
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    - Groundbreaking, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Slides [includes notes], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edward F. Dobihal, Jr., Lecture on Religion and Health [brochure], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hospice Institute of Education Training and Research, Inc., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hospice [notes and taped interview with unidentified woman regarding unidentified hospice], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Hospice Organization, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - St. Christopher's Hospice
    - General, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Report [by Dobihal; tape], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Slides, 1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional material, Accession 2002-M-034
  - Citizens Concerned for Compassionate Care (CCCC)
    - General [includes photographs of meeting on 1999 Sep 16], 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Audiocassettes of meetings, 1999
      - Hospice move?, 1999 September 6; 1 (Box 1A)
      - Open meeting (tape one), 1999 December 5; 1 (Box 1B)
      - Open meeting (tape two), 1999 December 5; 1 (Box 1C)
    - Topographical maps [of original site of hospice in Branford, Connecticut] (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    - Award of distinction, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Clinical pastoral education committee, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Clinical pastoral education student handbook, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Dissertation "Bereavement and the Church's Ministry", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - Snoke, Albert and Parnie [memorial services materials, including photographs], 1973-1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Additional material, Accession 2002-M-062
  - As Long as There is Life—" A Story about Pat, Dick, Rick, and Mark Forest and the Hospice Home Care Team Who Shared Their Lives (produced by Alberta Jacoby), 1980; 1 (Box 1)
    - Duplicating master, 1 (Box 1-D)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 1U)
      - "Study and Discussion Guide" which accompanies the film; a Family Life Film Award presented by the National Council on Family Relations, Circa 1980 (Box 2)
- Additional material, Accession 2007-M-001
  - Citizens Concerned for Compassionate Hospice Care (CCCHC)
    - General, 1971-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - Donations, 1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters etc., arranged by date [original folder title], 1991-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Connecticut Hospice, Inc.
    - General, 1974-2005, undated (Box 2, Folder 9-14)
    - Clippings, 1999-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)